Guide to the Harold J. Morowitz papers, 1944-2010
George Mason University Libraries
Special Collections and Archives, George Mason University
Harold J. Morowitz papers
1944-2010
George Mason University. Special Collections and Archives.
Harold J. Morowitz
C0049
5 linear feet (15 boxes)
The collection includes a draft copy of Energy Flow in Biological Systems, including chapter and appendix notes, calculations for mathematical operations, and correspondence between the author and his editor; a draft copy of Beginnings of Cellular Life, including the index and notes; a draft copy of The Facts of Life with the author's copy and the original artwork for the illustrations; and working papers, correspondence, and other documents pertaining to his academic career including original poetry written by Morowitz.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Collection donated by Harold Morowitz in 1997-1998. Additional donation by Harold Morowitz in 2011.
Biographical Information
Harold J. Morowitz is a biophysicist and Robinson Professor in Biology and Natural Philosophy at George Mason University. Born in Poughkeepsie, N.Y., on December 4, 1927, Morowitz earned his Ph.D. at Yale University in 1951. From 1951-1953 he was a physicist at the National Bureau of Standards. Morowitz was on the staff of the National Heart Institute from 1953-1955 before joining the faculty of Yale University in 1955. At Yale, Morowitz was associate professor of biophysics (1960-1968), professor of molecular biophysics and biochemistry (1968-1988), and master of Pierson College (1981-1986). He joined the faculty of George Mason University in 1988 as a Robinson Professor. Since 1993, Morowitz has directed the Krasnow Institute for Advanced Study. Dr. Morowitz has authored and coauthored several books: Life and the Physical Sciences (with Waterman), 1964; Theoretical and Mathematical Biology, 1965; Energy Flow in Biology, 1968; Entropy for Biologists (with Lucille Morowitz), 1970; Life on the Planet Earth,1974; Ego Niches,1977; Foundations of Bioenergetics, 1978; The Wine of Life, 1979; Mayonnaise and the Origins of Life, 1985; Cosmic Joy and Local Pain, 1987; The Thermodynamics of Pizza, 1991; Beginnings of Cellular Life (with James Trefil), 1992; The Facts of Life, 1992; and Entropy and the Magic Flute, 1993.
Scope and Content
The collection includes a draft copy of Energy Flow in Biological Systems, including chapter and appendix notes, calculations for mathematical operations, and correspondence between the author and his editor; a draft copy of Beginnings of Cellular Life, including the index and notes; a draft copy of The Facts of Life with the "author's copy" and the original artwork for the illustrations; and working papers, correspondence, and other documents pertaining to his academic career including original poetry written by Morowitz.
Arrangement
This collection is arragned alphabetically by subject.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Special Collections and Archives also holds the and the.
Index Terms
Persons:
Morowitz, Harold J.
Corporate Names:
George Mason University--Faculty.
Subjects:
Biochemistry.; Biophysics.; College teachers--Virginia--Fairfax.; Molecular biology.
Contents List
- Harold J. Morowitz papers
  - Photos (Folder 1, Box 1)
  - Petition to Adlai Stevenson from Yale scientists and related correspondence, 1956-57. (Folder 2, Box 1)
  - Some calculations (Folder 3, Box 1)
  - Chapters V and VI (Folder 4, Box 1)
  - Chapter III (Folder 5, Box 1)
  - Calculations- Chapter IV (Folder 6, Box 1)
  - Draft: Energy Flow in Biological Systems (Folder 7, Box 1)
  - A Thermodynamic Characterization of Self Reproduction (article) (Folder 8, Box 1)
  - Lipids (Folder 9, Box 1)
  - Appendix II (Folder 10, Box 1)
  - Dr. Morowitz- Notes- Correspondence (Folder 1, Box 2)
  - Dr. Morowitz- Notes (Folder 2, Box 2)
  - Chapters III and IV (Folder 3-4, Box 2)
  - Notes for Chapters IV and V (Folder 5-6, Box 2)
  - Draft- Beginnings of Cellular Life: Metabolism Recapitulates Biogenesis (Folder 1, Box 3)
  - Drafts (Index etc.)- Beginnings of Cellular Life (Folder 2, Box 3)
  - Index for page proof of proof (Folder 3, Box 3)
  - Draft: The Facts of Life (Folder 4, Box 3)
  - The Facts of Life: Author's Copy (Folder 5, Box 3)
  - Photosynthesis (Folder 1, Box 4)
  - Salt melting (Folder 2, Box 4)
  - Prince William Institute (Folder 3, Box 4)
  - NCRR (Folder 4, Box 4)
  - Publication (Folder 5, Box 4)
  - Frogs (Folder 6-7, Box 4)
  - Peace Agency (Folder 1, Box 5)
  - Morowitz to Paine 6-4-69 (Folder 2, Box 5)
  - Quastler, Henry (Folder 3, Box 5)
  - Theoretical Biology Committee (Folder 4 A, Box 5)
  - Theoretical Biology Colloquium- Traverse City, MI, 1968 (Folder 4 B, Box 5)
  - Biology Training for Apollo Astronauts (Folder 5, Box 5)
  - Medvedev (Folder 6, Box 5)
  - Bronowski (Folder 7, Box 5)
  - A Germ of Truth- Manuscript (Folder 8, Box 5)
  - Logue, Frank (Folder 9, Box 5)
  - Naugle, John- NASA (Folder 10, Box 5)
  - Watson- Sinshiemer (Folder 11, Box 5)
  - Kendrew, John (Folder 12, Box 5)
  - Gell Mann, Murray (Folder 13, Box 5)
  - Sagan, Carl (Folder 14, Box 5)
  - Palade, George (Folder 15, Box 5)
  - Thomas, Lewis (Folder 16, Box 5)
  - Mitchell, Peter (Folder 17, Box 5)
  - Nobel Prize (Folder 18, Box 5)
  - Lipmann, Fritz (Folder 19, Box 5)
  - Woese, C. R. (Folder 20, Box 5)
  - Grasso, Ella (Folder 21, Box 5)
  - Re, G. B.- Vatican (Folder 22, Box 5)
  - Altman, Sidney (Folder 23, Box 5)
  - Snyder, Gary (Folder 24, Box 5)
  - Invitation- Prime Minister India to Professor H. J. Morowitz(Morowitz) 12-15-81 (Folder 1, Box 6)
  - Poem- "Mr. Swinburned Discovers TV," by Peg Bracken (Folder 2, Box 6)
  - Le Ronde- Poems by Harold J. Morowitz (Folder 3, Box 6)
  - Correspondence (poetry)- Harold J. Morowitz and Michael McClure (Folder 4, Box 6)
  - Murray Gell- Man Birthday (Folder 5, Box 6)
  - Correspondence- Sagan, Carl to Morowitz, Harold J. regarding Venus and Mars (Folder 6, Box 6)
  - News clippings- Arkansas Creation Trial (Folder 7-9, Box 6)
  - Civil Liberties- ACLU, Louisiana (Folder 10, Box 6)
  - ACLU (Folder 11-12, Box 6)
  - Gary Snyder (Folder 13, Box 6)
  - The Ecology of Ego Niches- Manuscript (Folder 14, Box 6)
  - Post card- Beat Poets (Folder 15, Box 6)
  - Arrow, Kenneth J. (Folder 16, Box 6)
  - Planetary Biology Subcommittee (NASA) (Folder 1, Box 7)
  - Entry Talk- Poem: Biosphere II 9-26-93 (Folder 2, Box 7)
  - Michael McClure- "Minnie Mouse and the Tap Dancing Buddha" (Folder 3, Box 7)
  - Broadside- "Gloaming" by Michael McClure (Folder 4, Box 7)
  - Complexity- Editorial Board (Folder 5-6, Box 7)
  - Complexity, v.3, No.1, September/October 1997 (Folder 7, Box 7)
  - National Advisory Research Resources Council (Folder 8, Box 7)
  - Buckley, William F., Jr. 2-4-82 (Folder 9, Box 7)
  - Encyclopedia of Scientific Concepts (Folder 10 A-B, Box 7)
  - Committee on Science and Human Values (Folder 11-12, Box 7)
  - Creation-Science Research Center (Folder 13, Box 7)
  - Facts of Life (Folder 14-15, Box 7)
  - Hospital Practice Mail (Folder 1-3, Box 8)
  - Draft- The Kindly Dr. Guillotin (Folder 4, Box 8)
  - Biomatrix (Folder 5, Box 8)
  - Diffusion During Solvent Transport by Poiseuille Flow (Folder 6, Box 8)
  - Nutrient Transit Time Diversity: A Novel Measure of Ecological Organization and Stability (Folder 7, Box 8)
  - Competitive Exclusion: Application of a Biological Principle to Societies in Conflict (Folder 8, Box 8)
  - Some Theoretical Consideration on the Use of Indicator Time- Concentration Curves in Hemodynamic Studies (Folder 9, Box 8)
  - Gerald Edelman (Folder 10, Box 8)
  - Godel Numbers (Folder 11, Box 8)
  - Lord Snow (Folder 12, Box 8)
  - Journal of Irreproducible Results (Folder 13, Box 8)
  - Some Notes on the Problem of Uncertainty in Biological Measurements (Folder 14, Box 8)
  - Taming Combinatorial Explosion (Folder 15, Box 8)
  - Hospital Practice (Folder 16, Box 8)
  - The Mind The Brain and Complex Adaptive Systems (Folder 17, Box 8)
  - Publications (Folder 18, Box 8)
  - The Origin of Intermediary Metabolism (Folder 19, Box 8)
  - Self Replicating Machines (Folder 20, Box 8)
  - Emergences: Twenty-Eight Steps from Matter to Spirit by Harold J. Morowitz- Chapters 1 through 35 (Folder 1-35, Box 9)
  - Biomatrix (Folder 36, Box 9)
  - Another Talk- Anti-Chaos, Teleology, and Teilhard (Folder 37, Box 9)
  - New Program at NSF (Folder 1, Box 10)
  - [Research and Correspondence for Emergence] (Folder 2, Box 10)
  - Emergences- Edited Papers (Folder 3, Box 10)
  - Emergences- Preface (Folder 4, Box 10)
  - Emergences- Contents (Folder 5, Box 10)
  - Emergences- Chapters 1 through 16 (Folder 6-21, Box 10)
  - Emergences- Chapters 17 through 36 (Folder 1-20, Box 11)
  - Mycoplasma (Folder 21-22, Box 11)
  - Franklin Harold [Mitchell Bio] (Folder 1, Box 12)
  - Paul Boyer [Mitchell Bio] (Folder 2, Box 12)
  - Lars Ernster [Mitchell Bio] (Folder 3, Box 12)
  - [Williams] (Folder 4, Box 12)
  - [Biochemistry] (Folder 5, Box 12)
  - [E. C. Slater] (Folder 6, Box 12)
  - Kent Gabrial (Folder 7, Box 12)
  - Protons- Onsager (Folder 8, Box 12)
  - [Research Proposal] (Folder 9, Box 12)
  - [Publication List of Jennifer Moyle] (Folder 10, Box 12)
  - [Protons, Electrons, and Energy] (Folder 11, Box 12)
  - Sabbatical 80- Miscellaneous (Folder 12, Box 12)
  - [Oxidative Phosphoylations- Notes] (Folder 13, Box 12)
  - [Letter on Entropy Book] (Folder 14, Box 12)
  - [Correspondence: The Kindly Dr. Guillotin] (Folder 15, Box 12)
  - Hawaii Education [Unpublished Intro. to Merck's Medicine Manual, Popular Edition] (Folder 16, Box 12)
  - [Miscellaneous] (Folder 17, Box 12)
  - [Deposition of Harold J. Morowitz] (Folder 1-2, Box 13)
  - [Patent on Making Negative Ions] (Folder 3, Box 13)
  - [The Fifth Keilin Memorial Lecture] (Folder 4, Box 13)
  - [Bioenergetics] (Folder 5, Box 13)
  - Wikstrom (Folder 6, Box 13)
  - Van Dam (Folder 7, Box 13)
  - [Notes and Calculations] (Folder 8, Box 13)
  - [My Laboratory] (Folder 9, Box 13)
  - [Charts on a Experiment From Feb 2-8, 1961] (Folder 10, Box 13)
  - [Labor Party] (Folder 11, Box 13)
  - [Essay on Ivan Puluj] (Folder 12, Box 13)
  - [Physics 32b Class Notes, Relativity Dynamics] (Folder 13, Box 13)
  - [Physics 100 Notes] (Folder 14, Box 13)
  - Alamethicin Paper (Folder 15, Box 13)
  - [Miscellaneous Mitchell Biography] (Folder 16, Box 13)
  - [Mitchell Biography Information] (Folder 17, Box 13)
  - [Correspondence Between Mitchell and Williams] (Folder 1, Box 14)
  - Givens [Notes for Autobiography] (Folder 2, Box 14)
  - [Autobiography] (Folder 3, Box 14)
  - Protons [Mitchell's Bio] (Folder 4-5, Box 14)
- Accession 2012.102, 1944-2010
  - Accession 2012.102, 1944-2010 (Box 15)